Finding Aid for the Otto Fenichel papers, 1903-1953 LSC.1613
UCLA Library Special Collections
Otto Fenichel papers
1903-1953
UCLA Library Special Collections
Fenichel, Otto
LSC.1613
9 Linear Feet (18 boxes)
Otto Fenichel was born on December 2, 1897 in Vienna. He decided to become a psychoanalyst and began his training while a medical student. He received his MD from the University of Vienna in 1921 and moved to Berlin in 1922 to complete his training at the Berlin Psychoanalytic Institute. He traveled to the Soviet Union in 1929 and 1932 and in 1933 went to Oslo to undertake the training of psychoanalysts, and did the same in Prague two years later. Fleeing the Nazis, he moved to Los Angeles in 1938. Fenichel was a Marxist, and insisted that psychology needed to be studied in a societal context; publications include The Outline of Clinical Psychoanalysis (1934), Problems of Psychoanalytic Technique (1941) and The Psychoanalytic Theory of Neurosis (1945). The collection consists of manuscripts, abstracts, drafts, reviews, notes, correspondence, memorabilia, and ephemera of Fenichel, manuscripts and abstracts of other psychologists, newsletters, and papers of Hanna Fenichel. Many materials are in German.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Randi Markowitz, 1991.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942330143606533
Biography
Fenichel was born on December 2, 1897 in Vienna; MD, University of Vienna, 1921; at age 17, decided to become a psychoanalyst and began his training while a medical student; moved to Berlin in 1922 to complete his training at the Berlin Psychoanalytic Institute; appointed an assistant (1923) and a training analyst (1925) at the Berlin Psychoanalytic Clinic; traveled to the Soviet Union in 1929 and 1932; in 1933 went to Oslo to undertake the training of psychoanalysts, and did the same in Prague two years later; fleeing the Nazis, he moved to Los Angeles in 1938; Fenichel was a Marxist, and insisted that psychology needed to be studied in a societal context; publications include The Outline of Clinical Psychoanalysis (1934), Problems of Psychoanalytic Technique (1941) and The Psychoanalytic Theory of Neurosis (1945); he died on January 22, 1946.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of manuscripts, abstracts, drafts, reviews, notes, correspondence, memorabilia, and ephemera of Fenichel, manuscripts and abstracts of other psychologists, newsletters, and papers of Hanna Fenichel.
Materials in this collection are in English and German.
General note
The following online container list has the same content as the edited paper finding aid, but its arrangement may be different.
Psychoanalysts -- Archives.; Fenichel, Otto--Archives.; Fenichel, Hanna
- Series 1
  - The misapprehended oracle. (Box 2)
  - Abstracts by Fenichel. (Box 1, 15)
- Abstracts
- Series 2
- The counter-phobic attitude. (Box 2)
- Concerning respiratory introjection. (Box 2)
- Concerning isolation. (First draft). (Box 2)
- On the psychology of boredom (1). (Box 2)
- Über Trophäe und Triumph (2 copies). (Box 2)
- Trophy and triumph. Includes a Holograph. [Synopsis?]. (Box 2 & 5)
- Freud's psychoanalysis. (Box 2)
- Psychoanalytic method. (Box 2, 6 & 13)
- Ego strength and ego weakness. (Box 2)
- On masturbation. (Box 2)
- Kardiner, Abram. (Box 2)
- The study of defense mechanisms and the importance of psychoanalytic technique. Includes draft and final copy. (Box 2 & 13)
- Neurotic acting out. (Box 2)
- [Anorexia]. (Box 2)
- [Psychoanalytic theory of neuroses]. 2 copies. (Box 2)
- Theoretical implications of the didactic analysis. Includes draft and final copy. (Box 2 & 5)
- Short psychotherapy. 2 copies & remarks and 2 typescripts (one with holograph corrections). (Box 2 & 13)
- Bernfeld, Siegfried. Types of adolescence. (Box 2)
- Bernfeld, Siegfried. Die Formen der Disziplin in Erziehungsanstalten. (Box 2)
- Über die Psychoanalyse als Keim einer zukünftigen dialektisch-materialistischen Psychologie. Various copies including drafts, typescripts and photocopies. (Box 2 & 14)
- Der Trieb, sich zu bereichern. (Box 2)
- Zur Kritik des Todestriebes. (Box 2)
- Zu Reichs Buch Massenpsychologie des Faschismus. Various copies. (Box 2 & 5)
- Abstracts. (Box 2 & 10)
- Duplicates of papers read in English. (Box 2)
- Essays on the theory of sex discussion outline by Fenichel. (Box 2)
- Hanna Fenichel papers. (Box 3, 4, 7 & 8)
- Notebook dated, December 2, 1920. (Box 4)
- Car insurance policy, 1939. (Box 4)
- Anmeldebuch for Fenichel from the University of Berlin, 1920. (Box 4)
- Poetry notebook, 1938-1945. (Box 4)
- Memorabilia and ephemera. (Box 4)
- Letters to Fenichel, 1945-1946. (Box 5)
- 175 topics of discussion about Freud's Three contributions to the theory of sex. (Box 5)
- Psychoanalyse und Gesellschaftswissenschaften. (Box 5)
- [Synopsis for a play]. (Box 5)
- Edith Reni. Gegen den Strom. (Box 5)
- Two brief clinical contributions. (Box 5)
- Concerning the anxiety of the dead. (Box 5)
- From the terminal phase of an analysis. (Box 5)
- Introjection and castration complex. (Box 5)
- Identification. (Box 5)
- Concerning unconscious communication. (Box 5)
- The economic function of screen memories. (Box 5)
- Examples of dream analysis. (Box 5)
- On organ libidinization accompanying the defense against drives. (Box 5)
- The long nose. (Box 5)
- A dream analysis. (Box 5)
- Concerning the theory of psychoanalytic technique. (Box 5)
- Concerning defense against anxiety, particularly by libidinization. (Box 5)
- The analysis of a name-substitution after 20 years. (Box 5)
- On the compulsive doubt about death-news. (Box 5)
- Concerning the critique of the death instinct. (Box 5)
- A contribution to the psychology of jealousy. (Box 5)
- The economics of pseudologia phantastica. (Box 5)
- The black cook. (Box 5)
- Early stages of ego development. (Box 5)
- Other psychiatrist's manuscripts. (Box 5)
- Lists. (Box 6 & 10)
- On Reich's mass psychology, 1933. (Box 6)
- Los Angeles seminar / Int. Association, 1939-1940. (Box 6)
- Letters to Fenichel, December-January 1945-46.; About his books, plus reviews and related book material. (Box 6)
- Certificates for Fenichel from the K. K. Akademisches Gymnasium in Wien. (Box 6)
- Diskussionsbemerkungen - Revision der analytischen Pädagogik. (Box 6)
- Über kindliche Sexualitat. (Box 6 & 10)
- Diskussionsbemerkungen - Formen der Abwehr und der Ichreaktionen in der analyse. (Box 6)
- Gegenübertragung. (Box 6)
- Bartlett, Francis H. The limitations of Freud, 1940. (Box 6)
- Psc glossary? (Box 6)
- Problems of teaching psychoanalysis. (Box 6)
- Study group contract & papers relating to immigration to the United States of Fenichel's family. (Box 6)
- American Psychoanalytic Association. (Box 6)
- California Psychoanalytic Society. (Box 6)
- Replik auf Kaisers Antikritik über Der trotzhafte Charakter und Bemerkungen zu zeiner Arbeit Probleme der Technik. (Box 6 & 9)
- Bemerkungen zu Kaisers Der trotzhafte Charakter. (Box 6 & 9)
- American/California psychoanalytic society. (Box 6)
- Esoterik. (Box 6)
- Zur Angst vor der Toten. (Box 6)
- Psychoanalytic society. (Box 6)
- Fortschritte der Psychoanalyse, 1930-1936. (Box 6)
- Psychoanalytische Einfalle zu Engels Deutscher Baürnkrieg. 2 copies. (Box 6)
- Zu den Problemen der Technik. Various copies. (Box 6 & 13)
- Fromm, Erich: Autorität und Familie. Sozialpsychologischer Teil. (Box 6)
- Gedanken zu Freuds Der Mann Moses und die monotheistische Religion (Nur für den Hausgebrauch). (Box 6 & 13)
- R. Osborn: Marx and Freud, eine dialektische Studie. (Box 6)
- Zur wissenschaftsgeschichtlichen Stellung Freuds. (Box 6)
- Abschrift. Memorandum über die Deutsche Psychoanalytische Gesellschaft e. V. und das Berliner Psychoanalytische Institut. (Box 6)
- Correspondence with Dr. Walter C. Langer, 1941. (Box 6)
- Poetry, 1918-1943. (Box 6 & 12)
- Prague, 1936-1938. (Box 6)
- Various lists, certificates and ephemera. (Box 6)
- Reviews by Fenichel and others of books and articles. (Box 9)
- Die andere Liste. (Box 9)
- Reviews of articles by authors, D, F-G & F-L. (Box 9)
- Über Angstabwehr, insbesondere durch Libidinisierung. (Box 9)
- Zur Theorie der psychoanalytischen Technik. (Box 9)
- Die Wirksamkeit der psychoanalytischen Therapie. 2 copies. (Box 9)
- Portion of the Psychoanalytic theory of Neurosis. (Box 9)
- Fenichel's Austrian passport, valid, 1933-1938. (Box 10)
- Legal documents and correspondence concerning Fenichel family immigration to the U.S. (Box 10)
- Fenichel's school report book for, 1903-1907. (Box 10)
- Patient notes; lecture notes. (Box 10)
- Vor dem sexualakt.... (Box 10)
- Eigene Aufzeichnungen der Analysandin vor Wiederaufnahme der Analyse. (Box 10)
- Beitrag zur Psychologie der Eifersucht. (Box 10)
- Weiteres zur praeoedipalen Phase der Mädchen. (Box 10)
- Zur Ökonomik der Pseudologia Phantastica. (Box 10)
- Zur Psychologie der Langeweile. (Box 10)
- Schautrieb und Identifizierung. (Box 10)
- Two dream analyses. 2 copies. (Box 10)
- Analyse einer Namensverwechslung nach zwanzig Jahren. (Box 10)
- Eine Traumanalyse. (Box 10)
- Correspondence: Fenichel to others,, A-Z., 1943 (Box 11, Box 12)
- Correspondence: Fenichel to others,, A-Z., 1944 (Box 11, Box 12)
- Correspondence: Fenichel to others,, A-Z., 1945 (Box 11, Box 12)
- Probleme der Technik. Kurs in Wien bis, Dezember 1936. (Box 12, Box 13)
- Newspaper clippings and taylor's bill. (Box 12)
- Correspondence: Fenichel to Giesl Stein, 1938-1945. (Box 12)
- Correspondence: Fenichel to others, 1936 & 1941-1942. (Box 12)
- Correspondence: Fenichel to Walter Langer, 1941. (Box 12)
- Envelope containing various certificates. (Box 12)
- Internship / Citizenship. (Box 12)
- Letter from F. Kramer,; Letter from Edith, 1936 n.d. (Box 12)
- Address book. (Box 12)
- Map of part of eastern Austria. (Box 12)
- Envelope containing unidentified certificates. (Box 12)
- Unidentified part of a typescript. (Box 13)
- Ich begnüge mich wegen der Kürze der Zeit mit einem kurzen Beispiel. (Box 13)
- The importance of the study of defense mechanisms for psychoanalytic technique. (Box 13)
- On stage acting. 3 typescript copies (one with holograph corrections). (Box 13)
- Schultz-Hencke [?]. (Box 13)
- Untitled manuscript. (Box 13)
- Allgemeine Neurosenlehre. (Box 13)
- Probleme der Technik. Hollandische psychoanalytische Vereinigung. (Box 13)
- Some remarks on Freud's place in the history of science, 1946 [?]. (Box 13)
- The clinical aspect of the need for punishment. (Box 13)
- Trauma der Geburt. Rank. (Box 13)
- Part of Freud's psychoanalysis [?]. (Box 13)
- Freud's psychoanalysis. English and German., 2 copies each. (Box 13)
- Autorität und Familie sozialpsychologischer Teil. (Box 13)
- Freud, die endliche und unendliche Analyse. (Box 13)
- Freud, die endliche und unendliche Analyse. (Nur für den Hausgebrauch). (Box 13)
- A note on the phallic significance of the tongue and of speech. (Box 13)
- Über libidinöse Typen. (Box 13)
- Flugel. Some unconscious factors in the international language movement with special reference to Esperanto. (Box 13)
- Freud, Anna. Das Ich und die Abwehrmechanismen. (Box 13)
- Psychoanalyse der Politik. (Box 13)
- Unidentified typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 13)
- Remarks about the common phobias. Various copies including a holograph, typescripts and typescripts with holograph corrections. (Box 13)
- Sleep disturbances. (Box 13)
- Unidentified manuscripts. (Box 13, Box 14)
- Marital situation as resistance. (Box 13)
- Neurotic disturbances of sleep. Discussion. (Box 13)
- Angstabwehr. (Box 13)
- Zur Ps-A der Lüge. (Box 13)
- Regression to childhood. Typescript. Pages 5-7 and 18-22 only. (Box 13)
- Methode. (Box 13)
- Homosexuality. (Box 13)
- I am very glad to have the opportunity..... (Box 13)
- Rundbriefe. Fragments. 5 folders. (Box 14)
- Correspondence. Fenichel to Edith Ujvari, 1939-1941. (Box 14)
- Contribution to the discussion in Chicago, May 3, 1942. (Box 14)
- Various unidentified typescript pages. (Box 14)
- Part of unidentified typescript. (Box 14)
- Correspondence. Fenichel to Balint, May 30, 1935. (Box 14)
- Unidentified typescript. Missing page 1. (Box 14)
- Norsk - Dansk psykoanalytisk forening. (Box 14)
- Notes. Susan F. Alexander. (Box 14)
- Über Erziehungsmittel. (Box 14)
- Theorie Erziehungsmittel. (Box 14)
- Gymnastik., vol.1, no.5/6., June 1926 (Box 14)
- Psychoanalytische betrachtungen zur Wirkungsweise der Gymnastik. (Box 14)
- Gymnastik. Manuscript. (Box 14)
- The means of education. Notes, drafts, and drafts with corrections. (Box 14)
- Various unidentified manuscript and typescript pages. (Box 14)
- Farrow, E. Pickworth. A method of self-analysis. Abstract. (Box 14)
- Federn-Meng. Das psychoanalytische Volksbuch. Abstract. (Box 14)
- Feigenbaum, Dorian. A case of hysterical depression. Mechanisms of identification and castration. Abstract. (Box 14)
- Bewusstseinsfremdes Erinnerungsmaterial in Traume. (Box 14)
- Bemerkungen zu einigen neüren psychiatrischen libeike, die du Psychoanalyse betreffen. (Box 14)
- Chadwick, Mary. A case of kleptomania in a girl of ten years. Abstract. (Box 14)
- Cohn, Max. Grenzen und Mystizismus in der Psychoanalyse. Abstract. (Box 14)
- Abraham, Karl. Versuch einer Entwicklungsgeschichte der libido auf grund der Psychoanalyse seelischer Störungen. Abstract. (Box 14)
- Glover, Edward. Notes on oral character formation. Abstract. (Box 14)
- Glover, Edward. A technical form of resistance. Abstract. (Box 14)
- Glover, Edward. The neurotic character. Abstract. (Box 14)
- Glover, James. Notes on an unusual form of perversion. Abstract. (Box 14)
- Lazar, Erwin. Medizinische grundlagen der Kulpädogogik. Abstract. (Box 14)
- Levine, Israel. Das Unbewurßte. Abstract. (Box 14)
- Low, Barbara. The cinema in education. Abstract. (Box 14)
- Balint, Michael. Psychoanalyse und klinische Medizin. Abstract. (Box 14)
- Bernfeld, Siegfried. Einige spekulative Bemerkungen über die psychologische Bewertung kleptothischer prozeße. Abstract. (Box 14)
- Die psychischen heilmittel [?]. (Box 14)
- Bryan, Douglas. Speech and castration: two unusual analytic hours. Abstract. (Box 14)
- Burrow, Trigant. Psychoanalytic improvisations and the personal equation. Abstract. (Box 14)
- Burrow, Trigant. Our mass neurosis. Abstract. (Box 14)
- Wittels, Fritz. Die Technik der Psychoanalyse. Abstract. (Box 14)
- Schakel, Julius. Enticklung der Wissenschaft vom Leben. Abstract. (Box 14)
- Schmitt, T.L. Iten und Charakter. Abstract. (Box 14)
- Schroeder, Theodore. The psycho-analytic method of observation. Abstract. (Box 14)
- Simmel, Ernst. Grundsätzliches zum rample gegen. Abstract. (Box 14)
- Symons, N.J. A note on the formation of symbols. Abstract. (Box 14)
- Der begriff Trauma in der beatizen psychoanalyticher neurosenlehre. [?] (Box 14)
- Penrose, L.J. Some psycho-analytical notes on negation. (Box 14)
- Psychoanalytic remarks on Fromm's Escape from freedom. (Box 14 & 18)
- Rado Sandor: The psychoanalysis of pharmacothymia. (Box 14)
- Reich, Wilhelm. Der psychogene tic als onanieaquivalent. [?] Abstract. (Box 14)
- Röllenbleck, Ewald. Gymnastik und Psychoanalyse. Abstract. (Box 14)
- Röllenbleck, Ewald. Die Bedeutung der psychoanalyse für die Erziehung. Abstract. (Box 14)
- Der erste internationale Kongreß für Sexualforschung. (Box 14)
- Reich, Wilhelm: Der triebhafte Charakter eine psychoanalytische Studie sur Pathologie des ich. (Box 14)
- Zeitschrift für psychoanalytische Pädagogik. (Box 14)
- Kritik der Zeitschrift für psychoanalytische Pädagogik II. (Box 14)
- Paul Schilder: Das Unbewußte. (Box 14)
- Untitled play by Harry Sobotka, 1904. (Box 14)
- Rundbriefe: 11., February 12, 1935.; 2 copies (one has a photocopy of page 1). (Box 16)
- Rundbriefe: 12., 3 copies (one is a photocopy). (Box 16)
- Rundbriefe: 13., April 4, 1935.; 2 copies (one is a photocopy). (Box 16)
- Rundbriefe: 14., April 26, 1935.; 2 copies (one is a photocopy). (Box 16)
- Rundbriefe: 15., June 17, 1935.; 2 copies (one is a photocopy). (Box 16)
- Rundbriefe: 16., June 30, 1935.; 2 copies (one is a photocopy). (Box 16)
- Rundbriefe: 17., August 30, 1935.; 2 copies (one is a photocopy). (Box 16)
- Rundbriefe: 18. (#22?). (Box 16)
- Rundbriefe: 19., October 17, 1935.; 2 copies (one is a photocopy). (Box 16)
- Rundbriefe: 20., September 23, 1935.; 2 copies (one is a photocopy). (Box 16)
- Rundbriefe: 21., December 31, 1935. (Box 16)
- Rundbriefe: 22., January 27, 1936. (Box 16)
- Rundbriefe: 23-25, 27, 36 & 38. (Box 16)
- Rundbriefe: 26., May 18, 1936. (Box 16)
- Rundbriefe: 28., July 7, 1936. (Box 16)
- Rundbriefe: 32 [?]. 2 copies. (Box 16)
- Rundbriefe: 33., February 17, 1937. (Box 16)
- Rundbriefe: 35., April 28, 1937. (Box 16)
- Rundbriefe: 37., June 29, 1937. (Box 16)
- Rundbriefe: 39., September 11, 1937. (Box 16)
- Rundbriefe: 40., October 23, 1937. (Box 17)
- Rundbriefe: 41, 45, 51 & 60. (Box 17)
- Rundbriefe: 42., January 7, 1938. (Box 17)
- Rundbriefe: 43., February 14, 1938. (Box 17)
- Rundbriefe: 44., March 14, 1938. (Box 17)
- Rundbriefe: 46., April 7, 1938. (Box 17)
- Rundbriefe: 47., April 20, 1938. (Box 17)
- Rundbriefe: 48., June 25, 1938. (Box 17)
- Rundbriefe: 49., August 3, 1938. (Box 17)
- Rundbriefe: 50., September 10, 1938. (Box 17)
- Rundbriefe: 52., November 18, 1938. (Box 17)
- Rundbriefe: 53., December 30, 1938. (Box 17)
- Rundbriefe: 54., February 6, 1939. (Box 17)
- Rundbriefe: 55., March 12, 1939. (Box 17)
- Rundbriefe: 56., April 16, 1939. (Box 17)
- Rundbriefe: 57., May 3, 1939. (Box 17)
- Rundbriefe: 58., June 7, 1939. (Box 17)
- Rundbriefe: 58. First 12 1/2 pages., June 7, 1939.; 2 copies. (Box 17)
- Rundbriefe: 59., July 15, 1939. (Box 17)
- Rundbriefe: 66., April 15, 1940. (Box 17)
- Rundbriefe: 68., July 1940. (Box 18)
- Rundbriefe: 70., October 9, 1940. (Box 18)
- Rundbriefe: 71., October 15, 1940. (Box 18)
- Rundbriefe: 73. Photocopy., January 23, 1941. (Box 18)
- Rundbriefe: 74. Photocopy., March 1, 1941. (Box 18)
- Rundbriefe: 75. Photocopy., March 1, 1941. (Box 18)
- Rundbriefe: 76. Photocopy., April 27, 1941. (Box 18)
- Rundbriefe: 77., June 10, 1941. (Box 18)
- Rundbriefe: 96. Photocopy., March 15, 1943. (Box 18)
- Rundbriefe: 97., March 17, 1943. (Box 18)
- Rundbriefe: 98., May 7, 1943. (Box 18)
- Rundbriefe: 111., September 20, 1944. (Box 18)
- Rundbriefe: No #. (Box 18)
- Psychoanalysis of anti-Semitism., 7 drafts and copies. (Box 18)
- Psychoanalysis of neuroses. (Box 18)
- Psychoanalytic theory of neuroses, two evenings. (Box 18)
- Psychoanalysis of the character. (Box 18)
- The ego and the affects., 6 copies. (Box 18)
- Die symbolische Gleichung; Mädchen = phallus. (Box 18)
- The scopophilic instinct and identification. (Box 18)
- Freud translation committee. (Box 18)